# Hamza Khan

Islamabad, PK | +(92)3338500844 | hamza.khan018@outlook.com | www.linkedin.com/in/hamza-khan-

### **PROFILE**

A software sorcerer with almost 5 years of wizardry in the realms of tech, weaving spells in both startup cauldrons and corporate kingdoms. Master of multiple languages and frameworks, this code conjurer danced between worlds, from the lightning-fast pace of startups to the structured symphony of Fortune 500 domains. Once the architect of his own startup saga, this trailblazer embarked on an almost 2-year adventure before returning to the enchanting world of innovation. A relentless seeker of tech's Holy Grails, forever eager to unveil the secrets of cutting-edge technologies and wield this wisdom to illuminate the darkest corners of problems with insightful solutions.

## **EDUCATION**

# **Bachelor of Computer Science**

NUCES, Islamabad, PK

## **SKILLS**

- Project Management
- Strategic Planning & Execution
- Team Leadership & Development
- Scrum & Agile Methodologies

- System Architecture & Engineering
- Application Design & Development
- Continuous Process Improvement

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# **Solution Architect**

May 2022 - Present

June 2019

Protovoid Technologies, Islamabad, PK

Partnered cross-functionally at all levels to plan and lead development and enhancement of program and technologies related to mobile and web development in Transportation, AI and E-learning Industry. Headed project portfolio management and provided direction, oversight, coaching, and motoring to engineering and software development teams. Tech-stack we worked on was Angular, JavaScript (React, NextJS, NextJS, and NodeJS), Java (Spring Boot).

- Achieved timely deliver and cost-effectiveness in all the projects despite resource limitations surpassing \$300k in under a year, showcasing strategic acumen and business growth expertise.
- **Devised a pioneering sales and marketing expansion strategy**, instrumental in facilitating the company's growth trajectory.
- Oversaw recruitment, interviews, and adeptly managed a team of 12, fostering culture of productivity and motivation.
- Navigated project complexities, ensuring successful deliveries while effectively managing client expectations and project bottlenecks.
- Elevated brand presence through targeted initiatives across social media and traditional marketing channels.

# **Oracle BRM Developer**

January 2022 – May 2023

Jaffer Business Systems, Islamabad, PK

Hired to spearhead Oracle's program for planning, design, engineering, and implementation of Oracle BRM to replace Huawei CBS for Telenor Pakistan. Led multiple teams to deliver a module known as Batch. Trained colleagues and customer on Cloud Computing and Scalability of our system. Tech-stack was Java (Spring Boot), RUST, and C++.

- **Delivered corporation's first data warehouse solution** based on Oracle BRM after prior failed attempts and enabled corporate collaboration. Helped corporate to perform analysis of their prepaid customer Call, SMS or Data usage.
- **Improved the analytics** for the corporate by devising a solution based on the ELK stack and implemented it with multiple modules.
- **Limited network traffic** by leading design and build of asynchronous functionality with caching and event-based functionality on top of microservice implementation.
- Modernized distribution of customer data to internal applications and minimized code duplication by steering development of multiple methods of distribution, including RESTful APIs.

# **Software Development Engineer**

Fiber Mountain, Islamabad, PK

Although a short-lived appointment but was the best 4 months of my career. Worked as a backend developer specializing in integrating artificial intelligence into the physical layer of customer's network. The company shut down it's operations in October 2021. Tech-stack was Java (J2EE and Spring Boot), and Ruby on Rails.

- **Designed a revamp strategy** for the backend to move from J2EE to Java Sprig Boot. Worked on design document and the timelines for achieving the proposed solution.
- **Devised changes to improve and stabilize** the product. Participated in code reviews and encouraged Pair Programming.
- **Improved the quality** of the product to 35% working closely with the SQA Team implementing BDDs.

# **Software Development Engineer in Test**

December 2019 – May 2021

S&P Global, Islamabad, PK

A company where your analytical opinions truly matter and each person who works here has an essential role in S&P Global reputation of integrity, transparency, and excellence. Worked in the Xpressfeed team improving the quality of the product with automation. Tech-stack was Java (cucumber), Python (Django and pytest), C# (.Net Core and Blazor).

- **Actively contributed to an in-house test framework enabler** known as Centralized Automation Framework Enabler (CAFE) which was used to facilitate the automation tests.
- Improved monitoring of the automation test cases for 25+ teams using custom Elasticsearch JavaScript client.
- **Delivered the implementation of Snowflake** as a new data warehouse for data population and retrieval. Participated in multiple database design calls. Scalability and availability of the database was addressed with all the modern check and balances. Ultimately got S&P Global President's recognition on our achievement.
- Participated in intracompany hackathons implementing solutions on frameworks like Blazor, Dockers, Kubernetes and custom-tailored Machine Translator solution using Encoder-Decoder Recurrent Neural Networks with Attention.
- **Provided value to the business** by participating in the revamping of Xpressfeed from JavaFX to a web based Angular-Spring Boot solution. Worked on the design document for the new version of the product.

# **Software Development Engineer**

June 2019 – November 2019

Rockville Technologies, Islamabad, PK

Hired as a fresher in the Immediate Voice Response (IVR) team providing solutions to the telecom sector in Pakistan. Implemented Asterisk as an IVR solution and worked on multiple languages like Java, and Python. Helped new recruits get onboard on our platform and planned their onboarding routine. Tech-stack was Java (Spring Boot), Perl, Python, and PHP.

- Automated different workflows with Selenium based windows automation framework known as Winium which was a solution used by our SQA team.
- Got introduced to the microservice architecture and revamped multiple legacy applications on Spring Boot microservice architecture. Improved legacy scripts written in Perl, Python, and PHP.
- **Regular usage of middleware APIs** exposed by telecom companies to provide billing and request customer related information to be integrated in our VAS Services.
- **Started the design and development phase of BAJAO**, worked closely with my team to implement the database ERD and worked on the data layer microservices.

## Honors/Rewards

- Second place at NaSCon 2016 in Battle of Brains
- Lead a team that won IBM Hackathon 2017 using IBM Bluemix Services
- Runner up at NaSCon 2018 in AI GAME BOT Competition
- Competed in Telenor Hackathon 2018
- Competed in MLH Local Hack Day 2018, using Microsoft Azure Services
- Competed in JAZZ CIVIC Hackathon 2018
- Runner up at NaSCon 2019 in Mobile Development Competition
- Competed in intracompany DevOps Hackathon 2020
- Competed in intracompany Market Intelligence I3 Contest 2020
- Competed in Hacker Earth Recruit-A-Thon 2020

June 2021 – October 2021